Guide to the Educational Facilities Committee records, 1962-1986 UA.03.02.0015
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Educational Facilities Committee records
1962-1986
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Educational Facilities Committee
UA.03.02.0015
5 Linear Feet
The Educational Facilities Committee at Duke University was created in 1962 as a standing committee of the University Committee on Long-Range Planning. The Educational Facilities Committee was appointed by the President and concerned itself with supplying adequate educational facilities to meet the needs of educational programs. In 1986, the Educational Facilities Committee and the Chancellor's Environmental Concerns Committee were combined to form the University Committee on Facilities and Environment. Committee chairs include Frank T. de Vyver (1962-1974), Frederick C. Joerg (acting 1969, 1972), George W. Williams (1974-1981), George Pearsall (acting 1977), and Calvin Ward (1981-1986). The collection consists of correspondence, memoranda, reports, minutes, clippings, charts, projections, blueprints, and maps of the Educational Facilities Committee. Major subjects include student housing and dining facilities, the Arts Center, landscaping, the Medical Center, the Art Museum, auditoria, libraries, space assignment and relocation, athletic facilities, and the University Center. English.
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Educational Facilities Committee records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1975-1987.
Historical Note
The Educational Facilities Committee was constituted on October 24, 1962 as a standing committee of the University Committee on Long-Range Planning. The committee was appointed by the President and consisted of two faculty members, the Vice Provost for Professional Schools, the Assistant Provost of Planning and Institutional Studies, the Secretary of the University, the Business Manager (Executive Secretary) and the Assistant Superintendent of Duke Hospital. The President of the University and the Provost served as ex-officio members. Frank T. de Vyver, Vice Provost for Professional Schools and Professor of Economics (and Chair of that Department) served as the Committee's first chairman.
According to the original charge, the Educational Facilities Committee was concerned with the consideration of educational programs and needs to be accommodated by new or renovated facilities for educational purposes. In these duties the committee reported to the Long-Range Planning Committee. The Committee also assumed the duties of the then-defunct Space Allocations Committee and reported directly to the President of the University. By 1970, the Committee had broadened its definition to consider and review all matters relating to the physical and functional changes in the buildings and grounds of the University. The Committee also dealt with the task of naming, and in certain cases renaming, buildings, lecture halls, corridors, exhibition galleries, and rooms. The Committee also served as a board of appeals for space arguments within the University.
During the Committee's existence several members of the University faculty served as Chairman. These include: Frank T. de Vyver, Vice Provost, who served from 1962-74, Vice Chair of the committee, Frederick C. Joerg, Professor of Forest Management, served as acting chair in 1969 and 1972, George W. Williams, Professor of English, (1974-1981), George Pearsall, Professor of Mechanical Engineering, who served as acting chair in 1977, and Calvin Ward, Vice Provost (1981-1986).
The Committee authorized a number of subcommittees including, the Arts Center, Audio-Visual, Auditoria, Campus Planning Study, Chemistry Building, Dormitories (East and West Campuses), East Campus (Woman's College), Engineering Building, Graduate Affairs, Facilities for Institutional Advancement, Landscaping and Grounds, Men's Graduate Center, Traffic and Parking, University Center, and West Campus Physical Education Committees. In 1986, during the presidential administration of H. Keith H. Brodie, the Educational Facilities Committee and the Chancellor's Environmental Concerns Committee were combined to form the University Committee on Facilities and Environment.
Collection Overview
The collection consists of records relating to the building, renovation, and maintenance of the physical plant of the University, as addressed by the Committee. Correspondence, memoranda, reports (typed and annotated), minutes, clippings, charts, projections, blueprints, and maps comprise the collection. There exists some material that predates and postdates the span dates of this collection. Although most of the material was created during the general functioning of the Committee, there exists some material not produced by this organization. This material includes letters, reports, booklets, and clippings. Major subjects include student life (dorms, dining halls, student center), the Arts Center, landscaping, the Medical Center, the Art Museum, auditoria, libraries, space assignment and relocation, athletic facilities, and the University Union.
Related Archival Materials note
Frank Traver De Vyver Papers, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Calvin L. Ward Papers, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
George W. Williams Papers, 1950-2005, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
University Committee on Long Range Planning Records, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Clippings (information artifacts); Projections; Maps; College buildings -- Planning; Dormitories -- North Carolina; Blueprints; Athletic fields -- North Carolina -- Management; College buildings -- Designs and plans; College buildings -- North Carolina; Duke University. Educational Facilities Committee; Duke University. Library; Duke University. Committee on Facilities and Environment; Duke University -- Buildings; Duke University -- Student housing; Duke University -- Administration; Duke University. Museum of Art; Duke University. Medical Center -- Buildings; Pearsall, George W.; Duke University. University Committee on Long-Range Planning; Williams, George Walton, 1922-; Ward, Calvin Lucian; De Vyver, Frank Traver, 1904-1980
- Minutes and Agendas, 1963-1986.
  - Minutes (Box 1)
    - 1963-1964 (Box 1)
    - 1964-1965 (Box 1)
    - 1965-1966 (Box 1)
    - 1967-1968 (Box 1)
    - 1968-1969 (Box 1)
    - 1969-1970 (Box 1)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 1)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 1)
    - 1973-1974 (Box 1)
    - 1974-1975 (Box 1)
    - 1975-1976 (Box 1)
    - 1976-1977 (Box 1)
    - 1977-1978 (Box 1)
    - 1978-1979 (Box 1)
    - 1979-1980 (Box 1)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 1)
    - 1981-1982 (Box 1)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 1)
    - 1983-1984 (Box 1)
    - 1985-1986 (Box 1)
  - Agendas
    - 1966-1974 (Box 1)
    - 1975-1986, undated (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1960-1986.
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes correspondence to and from the committee. The correspondence documents the spectrum of issues that the committee faced and was responsible for. Correspondence from 1960-1962 is of the Space Allocation Committee, the precursor of the Educational Facilities Committee. Major correspondents include the R. Taylor Cole, Chairman and member of the Long Range Planning Committee; Marcus E. Hobbes, member of the Long Range Planning Committee; Paul M. Gross, Vice President for Education; A. Hollis Edens, President of the University; Deryl J. Hart, President of the University; Frank T. DeVyver, Chairman of the Educational Facilities Committee; Alan K. Manchester, Dean of Trinity College of Arts and Sciences; Terry Sanford, President of the University; George W. Williams, Chairman; N. Allison Haltom, Secretary of the University; Calvin Ward, Assistant Provost; James Ward, University Architect; Douglas Knight, President of the University; Thomas Hayes, University Architect; H. Keith H. Brodie, President of the University; Everett Hopkins, Vice President of Institutional Advancement; faculty and staff of the University; contractors; and architects.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1960-1969 (Box 1)
  - 1970-1976 (Box 1)
  - 1977-1986, undated (Box 1)
- Subject Files, 1962-1986.
  Alphabetically arranged by building and subject.
  - Allen Building, 1962-1986 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Affairs/Admissions House, 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - American Dance Festival, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Animal Behavior Station, 1975 (Box 1)
  - AROD (North) Building, 1962-1986 (Box 1)
  - Art Building, 1975-1980 (Box 1)
  - Arts Center, 1962-1986, [5 folders] (Box 1)
  - Art Library, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Art Museum (Science Building), 1967-1980 (Box 1)
  - Asbury House, 1965-1974 (Box 1)
  - Audio-Visual Aids, 1964-1967 (Box 1)
  - Auditoria, 1964-1975 (Box 1)
  - Baldwin Auditorium, 1964-1977 (Box 1)
  - Mary Duke Biddle Music Building, 1968-1974, [3 folders] (Box 2)
  - Biological Science Building, 1977-1980 (Box 2)
  - Branson Theatre, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Bivens Building, 1974-1980 (Box 2)
  - Building and Grounds Committee of the Board of Trustees, 1969-1976, [2 folders] (Box 2)
  - Card Gymnasium, 1963-1966 (Box 2)
  - Carr Building, 1968-1980 (Box 2)
  - Chapel, 1972-1982 (Box 2)
  - Coffee House, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Commission on Faculty Reorganization, 1952 (Box 2)
  - Committee on Student Life, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Community Health Sciences Building (Pickens), 1968 (Box 2)
  - Computer Printouts [Room Specifications], 1967-1983 (Oversize-box 5)
    This file contains printed specifications of all rooms on campus. The printouts present information such as the building location of the room, floor that the room is on, the department that has possession of the room, the height, length, width, square feet, and the use of the room. This file also contains a key, which describes how the rooms are classified and used.
  - Cool Storage Building, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Courses of Independent Study, undated (Box 2)
  - Crowell Hall, 1977-1980 (Box 2)
  - Denominational Centers, 1972-1980 (Box 2)
  - Dormitories, East Campus, 1962-1984 (Box 2)
  - Dormitories, West Campus, 1962-1986, [2 folders] (Box 2)
  - Duke Press, 1962-1967 (Box 2)
  - Duke University Transit Buses, 1977-1979 (Box 2)
  - East Campus, 1962-1986 (Box 2)
  - East Campus Gymnasium, 1962-1980 (Box 2)
  - East Campus Tennis Courts, 1979 (Box 2)
  - East Campus Physical Education Building, 1964 (Box 2)
  - East Campus Service Area, 1980 (Box 2)
  - East Campus Student Center, 1963-1964 (Box 2)
  - East Duke Building, 1962-1980 (Box 2)
  - Education Professions Development Act (Box 2)
  - Emeriti Offices, 1975-1981 (Box 3)
  - Engineering Building, 1962-1968, [2 folders] (Box 3)
  - Extramural Activities, 1949-1950, [2 folders] (Box 3)
  - Faculty Club, 1974-1976 (Box 3)
  - Robert Lee Flowers Building, 1967-1980 (Box 3)
  - Fuqua School of Business, 1985 (Box 3)
  - Gothic Dining Halls, 1966-1967 (Box 3)
  - Graduate School of Business Administration, 1977-1980 (Box 3)
  - Graduate Affairs Committee, 1962-1963 (Box 3)
  - Gray Building, 1966-1980 (Box 3)
  - Paul M. Gross Chemical Laboratory, 1964-1967 (Box 3)
  - Handicap Access, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Elizabeth P. Hanes House, 1966-1967 (Box 3)
  - Houses on Campus Drive, 1965-1980 (Box 3)
  - Houses on Erwin Road, 1964-1980 (Box 3)
  - Institutional Advancement Facilities, 1963 (Box 3)
  - Intramural Athletic Programs and Recreation, 1964-1965 (Box 3)
  - Landscaping, 1962-1980, [2 folders] (Box 3)
  - Language Building, 1973-1979 (Box 3)
  - Law School Building, 1977-1983 (Box 3)
  - Maps, 1962-1986 (Box 3)
  - Marine Laboratory (Beaufort, N.C.), 1963 (Box 3)
  - Medical Center, 1962-1986 (Box 3)
  - Old Chemistry Building, 1962-1986, [4 folders] (Box 3)
  - William R. Perkins Library Building, 1962-1980, [2 folders] (Box 3)
  - Physics/Mathematics Building, 1972-1977 (Box 3)
  - Plaques and Memorials, 1962-1986, [3 folders] (Box 3)
  - CRS Planning Study, 1964 (Box 3)
  - Post Office, 1974 (Box 3)
  - Pre-architectural planning program, 1964-1986 (Box 3)
  - Pre-Fab Houses, 1975-1976 (Box 3)
  - Science Building, 1963 (Box 3)
  - Signs and Signage, 1962-1983 (Box 3)
  - Siting Committee (Educational Facilities Committee), 1975 (Box 4)
  - Social Science Building, 1962-1980 (Box 4)
  - Sociology-Psychology Building, 1963-1978 (Box 4)
  - Southgate Craft Center, 1978 (Box 4)
  - Sculpture Studio, 1979 (Box 4)
  - Space, 1962-1986, [2 folders] (Box 4)
  - Traffic and Parking, 1979-1981 (Box 4)
  - Trailers, 1984 (Box 4)
  - Trent Drive Hall; Graduate Center, 1963 (Box 4)
  - Trinity College Bell, 1982-1983 (Box 4)
  - University Center, 1962-1978, [4 folders] (Box 4)
  - West Duke Building, 1965-1980 (Box 4)
  - West Union Building, 1963-1978 (Box 4)
  - Whitehead Institute, 1980 (Box 4)
  - Work Status Reports, 1975-1980, [2 folders] (Box 4)
- Reports, 1962-1986.
  This series contains twelve bound and unbound reports; some are internal, while others were prepared by sources outside of the University.
  - University Union, Schematic Design Program, November 1972 (Box 4)
  - University Planning Committee Report of the Physical Facilities Subcommittee, April 1972 (Box 4)
  - Report of the Subcommittee on the University Union, September 1971 (Box 4)
  - Duke University Planning Study, 1966 (Box 4)
  - State of North Carolina Higher Education Comprehensive Planning Program, Facilities Inventory and Utilization Study, 1976 (Box 4)
  - State of North Carolina Higher Education Comprehensive Planning Program, Facilities Inventory and Utilization Study, 1979 (Box 4)
  - Duke Planning Study, Phase I (draft), [1963] (Box 4)
  - Duke University Development Campaign Considerations of Basic Policy and General Strategy, 1950-1951 (Box 4)
  - Preliminary Draft of the Space and Program Study of the Duke University School of Medicine and Hospital, 1952 (Box 4)
  - Duke University Business School Program: A New Facility for Graduate Business Education, 1978 (Box 4)
  - Duke: A Summary of the Duke University Development Program, [1965] (Box 4)
  - Profile of Duke University, 1956-1976 (Oversize-box 5)
- Oversize Materials
  - Subject Files series (Oversize-box 5)
    - Computer printouts [room specifications], 1967-1983 (Oversize-box 5)
  - Reports series
    - Profile of Duke University, 1956-1976 (Oversize-box 5)